<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A project for an equitable and lasting peace. Designed in the year 1643. when the affairs stood in ballance before the second coming of the Scots into this kingdom, from a desire to have kept them out then. With a disquisition how the said project may now be reduced to fit the present conjuncture of affairs, in a letter sent to divers prudent persons of all sorts. For preventing the Scots bringing an army into England a third time, or making themselves umpires of our affaires. By a cordiall agreement of the King, Parliament, City, Army, and of all the people in this kingdome among our selves.</title>
            <author>Nethersole, Francis, Sir, 1587-1659.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 53 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89919</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N498</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E459_16</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203019</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R205087</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863123</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863123</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115305</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89919)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115305)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 73:E459[16])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A project for an equitable and lasting peace. Designed in the year 1643. when the affairs stood in ballance before the second coming of the Scots into this kingdom, from a desire to have kept them out then. With a disquisition how the said project may now be reduced to fit the present conjuncture of affairs, in a letter sent to divers prudent persons of all sorts. For preventing the Scots bringing an army into England a third time, or making themselves umpires of our affaires. By a cordiall agreement of the King, Parliament, City, Army, and of all the people in this kingdome among our selves.</title>
                  <author>Nethersole, Francis, Sir, 1587-1659.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales, Army.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeare 1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed on p. 7: P.D., i.e. Sir Francis Nethersole.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>With an additional title page introducing the main text.</note>
                  <note>Includes an excerpt from the Army's declaration of 14 June 1647.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aug. 17".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115305:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A PROJECT For an Equitable and laſting PEACE.</p>
            <p>Deſigned in the year 1643. when the affairs ſtood in ballance before the ſecond com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the <hi>Scots</hi> into this Kingdom, from a deſire to have kept them out then.</p>
            <p>WITH A Diſquiſition how the ſaid <hi>Project</hi> may now be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to fit the preſent conjuncture of affairs, <hi>In a Letter ſent to divers prudent perſons of all ſorts.</hi> For preventing the <hi>Scots</hi> bringing an Army into <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> a third time, or making themſelves Umpires of our affaires.</p>
            <p>By a cordiall Agreement of the King, Parliament, City, Army, and of all the people of this kingdome among our ſelves.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Pro me praeſente Senatus, hominumque praeteria viginti millia veſtem mutaverunt.— Quum omnes boni non recuſarent, quin vel pro me, vel mecum perirent, armis decertare pro mea ſalute nolui, quod &amp; vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere &amp; vinci luctuoſum reip. fore putavi.</p> 
               <bibl>Cicero in Orat. ad Quirit. poſt Redit.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Saluberimum eſt Reip. ſi magna Imperia diuturna non ſint, ut temporis modus imponatur quibus Juris non poteſt.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Tit. Liv.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the yeare 1648.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:115305:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:115305:2"/>
            <head>A LETTER ſent to divers prudent Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of all ſorts.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Humbly pray you to take the paines to peruſe firſt the Declaration of the Lords and Commons aſſembled in Parliament, of the fourth and his Majeſties of the twelfth of Auguſt. <hi>1642.</hi> After them the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations dedicated to the Lord Major and Aldermen of the City in the yeare <hi>1642.</hi> Comparing the ſecond ſheet ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of with a part of the Declaration of the Army of the <hi>14.</hi> of June <hi>1647.</hi> from thoſe words, [But becauſe neither the granting of this alone &amp;c.] to theſe [we deſire that the right and freedome of the people to repreſent &amp;c.] And in the laſt place the Project I ſend you with this, (built upon the ſame foundation: which was firſt layed in the Conſiderations, and which the army once thought firme enough to ſupport their hops of Common and equall right, and freedome to themſelves, and to all the freeborn people of this Land,) at as much leiſure as you may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine from your many other great occaſions, and with as much attention as you may think fit to beſtow upon a piece of no more worth, bearing theſe thoughts in your minde while you are reading it.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:115305:3"/>
            <p n="1">1. Whether it had not been honorable for the King and his Party, ſafe for the Parliament and theirs, and equita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for both, to have made a Peace upon the termes therin deſigned at the time of the writing thereof, which was up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the firſt newes of the <hi>Scots</hi> reſolution to come into <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> the ſecond time, and from a deſire to have kept them out then by agreeing among our ſelves.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Whether (under favour, and with all humbleneſſe be it written) it had not been more conducible to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation and eſtabliſhment of Religion in the Kingdomes of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> in Doctrine, Worſhip, Diſcipline and Government, according to the Word of God, (which ought to be the onely rule thereof) and to the extirpation of Popery, Superſtition, Haereſie, Schiſme, Prophaneneſſe, and whatſoever may be found contrary to found Doctrine and the power of godlineſſe: And to the preſervation and defence of the Kings Majeſties perſon, and authority, of the rights and liberties of the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> and the liberties and publique weale of this Kingdome, for the King and all the ſubjects thereof at that time to have come to a Peace among themſelves upon the ſaid deſigned termes, than to have continued the Warre by calling in ſtrangers to their reſpective aſſiſtance upon the terms pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed by one ſide, and in probability deſigned by the other.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Whether it may not be thought more expedient for the two Houſes of the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> and the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115305:3"/>whole people thereof, to come to an Agreement with his Majeſty upon the ſame terms at this time notwithſtanding the great alteration of affaires in their favour ſince the Project was deſigned, than either to ingage in a new War againſt the <hi>Scots,</hi> with ſuch a diviſion among Engliſhmen, as will be an indubitable conſequent, if not an antecedent therof, or to admit them to be <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mpires in the affairs of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> as they will become, if the differences between his Majeſty and his Engliſh Subjects ſhould by Gods mercy come to an Accommodation upon their third, as thoſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween his Majeſty and the <hi>Scots</hi> did upon their firſt bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an Army into this Kingdome.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Whether any, and what exception can be taken to the juſtice or equitableneſſe of any particular Article of the Project, even at this time, without having reſpect to the practicableneſſe thereof, whereof perhaps there may be leſſe doubt ere long, though I yet ſee no other ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent ground for it but this, that methinks the tide is turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Such are the revolutions of humane affairs.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, in caſe any of the ſaid Articles ſhall be judged though neither unjuſt, nor unequall, yet impracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable, as things now ſtand, whether the ſaid Project may not be reduced to fit the preſent conjuncture of affaires with ſome additions, abatements, or alterations; and what alterations, abatements, or additions may be found juſt and reaſonable for the two Houſes of Parliament to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115305:4"/>inſiſt upon, and for his Majeſty to yeeld unto in reſpect of the change and preſent ſtate of affairs.</p>
            <p>Secondly, to paſſe your cenſure, and let me know your ſenſe upon all the foreſaid particulars with the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of a freeman of this Kingdome, for whom I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it to be lawfull with due ſubmiſſion to thoſe in Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to conferre together in a private way about the beſt meanes to recover, and maintaine a laſting Peace in the Realm, eſpecially at a time when there is cauſe of feare that it may be yet longer diſcontinued by the coming in of ſtrangers in Armes, which is once more our condition at the preſent. And in particular, How you conceive the Militia may be ſetled ſo, as may bee honourable for the King, and yet ſafe for his Parliament and Kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> according as is deſigned in the Project. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the receipt of which favour from you I do hereby engage my ſelfe to make you a returne of my thoughts upon the fifth and laſt Article, and by way of Advance do now let you know that to the three firſt I ſhould make a ſhort Anſwer in the Affirmative, to the fourth in the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative.</p>
            <p>In the laſt place I do here promiſe you to keep your Anſwer to my ſelfe only if you ſhall ſo require me, or if I ſhal publiſh it with your leave, yet never to diſcover your name, if you ſhall command me to conceale it. In ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change of which promiſe I muſt crave one from you, to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:115305:4"/>ſuffer no Copie to be taken in writing, nor any new Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion to be made either of the Project, or of this Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, untill I may finde the ſeaſon opportune for the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lication of them, which I do not as yet. And for that reaſon though I ſend you them in Print, to eaſe the trouble of tranſcribing, I have made ſure to have all the Copies in my own keeping. And ſo I remaine</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Dated.</hi> 
                  <date>Iunii— <hi>1648.</hi>
                  </date> 
                  <hi>the Climacterical yeer of this Kingdome.</hi>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Sir, <hi>Your moſt humble ſervant P. D.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <head>Poſtſcript.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>UPon ſecond thoughts I finde it neceſſary for me to give you a briefe account why I did not publiſh this <hi>Project</hi> when it was firſt deſigned, nor in all the long time ſithence elapſed, and yet have thoughts of doing it now. You may therefore pleaſe to underſtand that my purpoſe at firſt was to have printed two Copies thereof, the one at <hi>London,</hi> the other at <hi>Oxford,</hi> to avoyde the great prejudice of being reputed partiall. But before I could effect this, it came to my knowledge that the writer of the Conſiderations had found meanes to have them put into the hands of certaine perſons of prime quality, and credit in both places, and had found that the corner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone of his Conſiderations, and of my <hi>Project</hi> (borrowed from him) was rejected by ſome of too great power on both ſides, as he foreſaw, and fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told it was like to be. This made me give over my purpoſe at that time. And from that time the Deſigne lay by me as a neglected and uſeleſſe piece, till the Army having gotten the King into their power, was upon their march from <hi>Newmarket</hi> with an intention (as was voyced) to have brought his Majeſty up to <hi>London</hi> without more ado. The apprehenſion I then had that this might prove very dangerous to the Common-wealth,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115305:5"/>(to the proſperity whereof, and of hit Majeſty, if I know my owne heart, it beateth with an equall pulſe) ſtirred me ſo farre that I was once more determined to have publiſhed my concept what, and no more was needfull to be tranſacted before his Majeſties returns to his Palace at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and to that end had ſent this ſimple <hi>Project</hi> to a Licencer. In this nick of time forth came the Armies Declaration of the <hi>4.</hi> of <hi>June 1647.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in finding the maine of what I had ever thought very expedient, if not altogether neceſſary, to be mainely inſiſted on by Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax,</hi> and his Officers and Souldiers, I was much rejoyced to ſee the work whereunto I deſired to have contributed my weake indeavours to be taken into abler hands, and there I left it. Whether his Excellency, and his chiefe Officers (for the opinion of his common ſouldiers and their Agitators is to me of no regard) be ſince fallen from what they then declared to be their deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berate, and determinate judgement, I leave Him, and them to give an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count to God, and the World. I am ſure tis commonly believed, that they onely made ſhew of being of the minde at large expreſſed in the foremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned Declaration to ingratiate themſelves with the Kingdome, till by that meanes they had quietly gotten all the ſtrength thereof into their own, and their parties hands: And that they are at preſent the moſt averſe of any other to a <hi>Perſonall Treaty</hi> at <hi>London.</hi> On the other ſide it is too mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, that the generality of the City, and Country, are perhaps too violent for his Majeſties coming thither without ingaging his Royall word to paſſe the three Praeparatory Bills, apprehended like to be of hard digeſtion to his Majeſty, and it is further apprehended that the two Houſes of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament may alſo happen to be divided upon this point. Perchance a middle way may be found as faire, and ſafe, as either of the former, and not impaſſable either with his Majeſty or with the two Houſes. This induced me now to ſubmit my conceipt to the cenſure of wiſer men. And if for the ground-work it ſhall be ſo happy as to receive any meaſure of approbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from any conſiderable number of ſuch as your ſelfe, it is not impoſſible that I may be thereby emboldened to expoſe it to the eye of the people, which I conceive to be ſharper than the ſight of any one, or of any few of the wiſeſt men of the Land. Sir, <hi>I</hi> crave your pardon for this addition to your trouble, and remained before, and ever.</p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:115305:5"/>
            <p>A PROJECT For an Equitable and laſting PEACE. </p>
            <p>Deſigned in the year 1643. when the affairs ſtood in the ballance.</p>
            <p>Printed in the yeare 1648.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="petition">
            <pb facs="tcp:115305:6"/>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:115305:6"/>
            <head>TO THE KINGS Moſt Excellent MAJESTIE: And to the LORDS and COMMONS aſſembled in PARLIAMENT.</head>
            <head type="sub">The humble petition of P. D. a plain Countreyman, a well-wiſher of the City, and lover of truth, righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe and peace, in his own name, and all theirs that may ſubſcribe hereunto.</head>
            <opener>Moſt humbly ſheweth,</opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat whereas in a Petition of both houſes of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment preſented to your Majeſty in the beginning of your Reigne it was declared, That they found it an undoubted right and conſtant priviledge of Parliament, that no member of Parliament, ſitting the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:115305:7"/>or within the uſuall times of Priviledge of Parliament, is to be impriſoned, or reſtrained without ſentence, or order of the Houſe, unleſſe it be for treaſon, felony, or for refuſing to give ſurety for the peace.</p>
            <p>And whereas in the Petition of right, made to your Majeſty by the Lords and Commons aſſembled in Parliament in the third yeer of your reigne, it was declared, That no offender, of what kind ſoever, is exempted from the proceedings to be uſed, and puniſhments to be inflicted by the Lawes and Statutes of this your Realme.</p>
            <p>And whereas by the expreſſe Lawes and Statutes thereof, that is to ſay, by the Statute called the Great Charter of the Liberties of England, and by a Statute made in the 28. yeere of the reigne of your moſt noble Progenitor King <hi>Edward</hi> the third, it is declared and enacted, That no Freeman may be taken or impriſoned but by the lawfull judgement of his Peers; or by the Law of the Land; nor without being brought to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer by due proceſſe of Law:</p>
            <p>And whereas by two other Acts of Parliament, the one made in the 38. yeer of your ſaid glorious anceſtor, it is ordained and aſſented That all they that make ſuggeſtions to the King him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, be ſent with the ſuggeſtions before the Chancellour, Treaſurer, and his great Councell, and that they there finde ſureties to purſue their ſuggeſtions, and that then proceſſe of the Law be made againſt the perſons in that manner accuſed; and that if he that maketh the complaint cannot prove his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent againſt the Defendant by the proceſſe limited as aforeſaid, he ſhall be commanded to priſon, there to abide till he hath made gree to the parry of his damages, and of the ſlander that he hath ſuffered by ſuch occaſion, and after ſhall make fine and ranſome to the King.</p>
            <p>According to, and by the meanes of which good Lawes and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:115305:7"/>Statutes ſo enacted and declared as aforeſaid, juſtice hath heretofore proceeded againſt all offenders without exception, and all innocent ſubjects of this kingdome, of what condition ſoever, have in former times found themſelves ſufficiently ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured againſt falſe accuſers, untill the moneth of <hi>January</hi> in the ſeventeenth yeere of your Majeſties reigne. At which time Articles of high treaſon and other miſdemeanours having by your Majeſties Atturney been preferred againſt certaine per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, among which Articles theſe two were the principall, That they have traitorouſly indeavoured to ſubvert the very Rights and being of Parliaments; and that for the compleating of their trayterous deſignes, they have indeavoured, as farre as in them lay, by force and terrour to compell the Parliament to joyne with them in their other trayterous deſignes, and to that end have actually raiſed and countenanced tumults againſt the King and Parliament: yet this heavy charge againſt the ſaid perſons, being themſelves members of Parliament, was not further proſecuted againſt them, neither was the ſuggeſtor thereof made knowne, through whoſe default it belongeth not to your Petitioners to inquire or judge, otherwiſe than in our private conſciences, ſo farre, as the ſaid default is one of the hinges upon which the juſtice of the late Warre hath been, and ought to be turned. But as one the one ſide we humbly conceive, that either juſtice ought to have been pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted againſt the ſaid accuſed perſons, and the ſuggeſtor of the ſaid Articles, according to the Lawes already in being; or if upon this occaſion there were any defect found in the above-recited Lawes and Declarations of Law, then ſome ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient proviſionall Ordinance in amendment of that defect might have been deviſed, and applyed to the preſent caſe by the wiſedome and authority of your Majeſty and your Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, that juſtice might have proceeded: So on the other
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:115305:8"/>ſide we hope we may preſume to ſay, (becauſe in truth we think,) that no inconvenience which might have occurred through any legall proceeding either againſt the ſaid accuſed perſons, or their ſecret accuſer, can any way countervaile the many miſchiefes, which have enſued upon the interruption thereof. For in your Petitioners poore obſervation grounded on divers Declarations of your Majeſty and of your two Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Parliament,(particularly that of your Majeſties of the twelfth of <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1642. and that other of the Lords and Commons of the beginning of the ſaid moneth,) the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of juſtice in this caſe firſt hath been the ſcandalous occaſion, whether given or taken, of a like ſtoppage in the caſe of many other offenders, and more eſpecially of ſome not long before, and of others ſoon after by Parliament accuſed of the ſame horrid crime of having intended force againſt the Parliament, which accuſation notwithſtanding was not further proſecuted againſt them. And this unluckie diſturbance of the due courſe of juſtice in the ſupreme Court and Councell of the kingdome, occaſioned a fatall diviſion in it and them, and was the true riſe of the two actions at Warre, the one between your Majeſty and your Parliament, and the other between the Parliament and your Majeſty, which hath ſince overrun this whole Land with ſuch violence, that no preeminence of the Crowne, or liberty of the Subject, how well eſtabliſhed ſoever, have been able to ſtand before it; But force throughout prevailing above right, a ſea of confuſed diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order brake in upon us, and a face of barbarous anarchy for a time covered this whole Realme.</p>
            <p>In tender conſideration whereof, and prevention of that utter deſolation, which muſt needs ſpeedily overwhelme this miſerable kingdome, if an other like floud of civill warre ſhould riſe upon it, your Petitioners humbly proſtrate at your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:115305:8"/>feet, do there implore your gracious protection: And do moſt humbly pray your Majeſty as they do alſo your Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that due and ſpeedy juſtice may paſſe upon all perſons, of what degree or quality ſoever, that may be found guilty of any intention of over-awing, or over-ruling your Majeſty or your Parliament before or ſince the beginning of the late War; the curſed iſſue of that higheſt miſdemeanour and treaſon can be deviſed againſt your Majeſty and this your kingdome: and reſpectively declared to be ſuch by your Majeſty, and by your two Houſes of Parliament. Or if this, in which there ſeemeth to have been ſome difficulty in time of peace, ſhould now be grown leſſe poſſible after ſo long a warre; That then for the time paſt your Majeſty of your owne Princely clemency, and by authority of your Parliament would be pleaſed to paſſe an act of oblivion, and to grant your full and free pardon to all the aforeſaid reſpectively accuſed perſons, and to all other that may be guilty of the ſame miſdemeanour and treaſon; as alſo to all thoſe that have been involved in the late warre through the failer of due and timely juſtice in thoſe originall and criticall caſes.</p>
            <p>And howſoever that for the time to come the Militia of the kingdome may by act of Parliament be for ever ſetled in ſuch a way, as may ſafegard the Parliament, and all the Members of both Houſes thereof, and above all your Majeſties ſacred per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon aſwell againſt all tumultuary aſſemblies of the people, as from all attempts by way of force, though under pretence of authority from the King. Which we humbly conceive is not impoſſible to be done without making a divorce between the Scepter and the Sword, which have been for ſo many ages joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in marriage by the providence of God, and Law of the Land. And that in and by the ſame act of Parliament ſevere defences may be made againſt all other unlawfull practiſes that
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:115305:9"/>may be found to be any way to the prejudice of that intire freedome, which ought to be maintained in all Parliamentary proceedings by all that wiſh well to their King or Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey.</p>
            <p>That immediately upon the paſſing of this Act, the whole ſouldiery in this kingdome may be diſbanded, the Committees for the ſafety of the reſpective Counties diſſolved, and that your Majeſty thereupon returning to <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> all other matters, either now in difference between your Majeſty and your Parliament, or between the two Houſes thereof, or men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in your Majeſties moſt gracious Meſſage of the twenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth of <hi>January</hi> 1641. or in any other Propoſitions and deſires either of your Majeſty or of the Lords and Commons, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally thoſe which concern the purity of Religion, &amp; of the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, and right government of his Church, may by the united authority of your Majeſty and of your Parliament be ſetled in ſuch a manner, that the Throne of the kingdome of Jeſus Chriſt may be erected in the due height thereof in this Realme, and the Throne of his Vicegerent therein may not be abaſed, nor any liberty of any the freemen of this kingdom in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fringed in the leaſt degree without your Majeſties and their free and full conſent in Parliament; it being (as we humbly conceive) altogether unjuſt and unlawful, and therfore clearly cannot be either profitable or durable for the Kings or Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of <hi>England</hi> to attempt the making of any change, even to the better, of the Lawes and preſent Government in any other faſhion.</p>
            <p>That (as the moſt probable and powerfull meanes to put an end to all ſtrife, and to prevent all partialitie, or ſuſpicion of partialitie in theſe ſupreme Reſolutions,) all the Members of both Houſes of Parliament may by an Ordinance be enjoyned to take ſuch an Oath as may be deviſed for the ſure binding
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:115305:9"/>them to give their Votes according to their conſciences in all things put to the queſtion. And that for the further ſecurity and comfort of your people, your Majeſty would be graciouſly pleaſed not onely to give free admittance to ſuch Committees of both Houſes of Parliament, as may be choſen by them hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to repreſent the reaſons of their Reſolutions to your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, and to give ſatisfaction to any doubts your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty upon adviſement with your Privy or Learned Counſel may have about them, before the giving of your concluſive voice, but that of your Princely grace you would condeſcend ſo farre as to oblige your ſelf likewiſe by a voluntary Oath not to deny any thing that to the beſt of your underſtanding ſo informed, as aforeſaid, ſhall be really for the good of your Subjects, and that may advance the true Proteſtant Religion, oppoſe Popery and Superſtition, ſecure the Law of the Land, (upon which is built as well your Majeſties juſt Prerogative, as the proprietie and libertie of the Subject,) confirme all juſt power and privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege of Parliament, and render your Majeſty and your people happy by a good underſtanding: which are your Majeſties owne gracious words of engagement in two of your Meſſages from <hi>Notingham.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That becauſe the deſires and mindes of the Commons of this kingdome cannot certainely be underſtood by the Votes of their Repreſentants in any one Parliament, (upon which, and many other prudent conſiderations it hath been by our wiſe Anceſtors provided, that the Parliament ought to be held at leaſt once every year; after the making of which proviſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it was long before any Parliament was continued to a greater length;) That it may be agreed, that immediately after the eſtabliſhment of all things aboveſaid in the manner aforeſaid, this preſent Parliament ſhall be diſſolved by the free conſent of both Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. But that before the diſſolution thereof there may be an
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:115305:10"/>Act paſſed for the aſſurance of an annuall Parliament in the ſame manner that a trienniall is now aſſured, with theſe neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary ſup plementall additions thereunto.</p>
            <p n="1">1. One for the regulating of Elections in ſuch a manner that they may be more free and leſſe chargeable, as well to the Countrey, as to the perſons in competition; and that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnes may not be ſo wholly in the power of the Sheriffe, and of that party he favoureth, as hitherto they have bin; and that ſome more ready, eaſie, and certaine way may be deviſed for the judgement of the lawfulnes and truth of returnes, then hath beene in uſe of late, to the manifeſt hazard of the publique liberty, if there ſhould be ſuch a conſpiracie of Sheriffes as may be imagined.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Another for the ſafe conducting of the Members of both Houſes of Parliament to the place appointed for the hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Parliament, and for their like ſafe return into their Countries, by the Sheriffs of the reſpective Counties through which they are to paſſe, being therunto required. But this only as oft as the Parliament may happen to be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled without any ſignification of the perſonall plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and command of the King for the time being.</p>
            <p n="3">3. And a third, as well for the prevention of the unſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble diſſolution of Parliaments without the conſent of both houſes, as for the aſſurance of the diſſolution of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Parliament within the ſpace of one yeere, and for the making of two Seſſions thereof at ſuch times, as by the two houſes ſhall be thought moſt convenient.</p>
            <p>That if it ſhall be made appeare upon ſufficient proofe that your Majeſties ſacred perſon was in any apparent danger, or hazard by thoſe tumults at Weſtminſter, which have been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaged for the reaſon of your departure from thence, that in that caſe it may be publiquely declared and recorded, that your Majeſty was not to blame in withdrawing your ſelfe from
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:115305:10"/>your Parliament there, the rather becauſe your Majeſty hath ſince been pleaſed to make many gracious offers to give a meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing again to your Parliament, if they would adjourne to any other place, and this as well before, as after the beginning of the late unnaturall Warre. But if upon due examination it ſhould be found that your Majeſties beliefe of the malice of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine perſons againſt your ſacred perſon, (which you thought you had too great reaſon to feare they intended to ſeize,) and of the evident danger not your ſelfe onely, but your Royall Conſort, and the Princes your children were in by the tumults raiſed and countenanced by the ſaid perſons hath been ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed only upon miſinformation, and that the failer of the timely diſcovery of the falſehood and maliciouſneſſe of ſuch informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion happened alſo through your Majeſties owne default, in not having taken the courſe by Law directed to that end; that in this caſe your Majeſtie of your owne meere motion may be graciouſly pleaſed to acknowledge, and command this to be publiquely recorded as an errour, for the preventing of the like in future times.</p>
            <p>That if all, or any of the Lords, Knights, Citizens and Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſſes, who before, or after the beginning of the late Warre withdrew themſelves from the Parliament, cannot make it e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidently appeare that they could not continue there with ſuch ſafety of their perſons, and plenary freedome of voting, as all members of Parliament of right ought to enjoy, that in this caſe they, or ſuch of them as ſhall faile in full proof of the point aboveſaid, may for ever be diſabled to fit againe in this, or any future Parliament in this kingdome; and may be further cenſured in ſuch a manner, as to the wiſedome of the reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Houſes of Parliament ſhall ſeeme juſt and meete. And that howſoever no ſuch Member of either Houſe may be read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted without making a publique acknowledgment of, and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:115305:11"/>ſubmiſſion for their faults, no danger, how great or certaine ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, being ſufficient to excuſe them for having failed in their duty to their King &amp; country, either by concealing their minds, or by deſerting their ſtations, before any one of them loſt any one drop of his bloud, which hath been the occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſo much bloudſhed of their fellow ſubjects: It being viſible that there could have been no breach between your Majeſty and your two Houſes of Parliament, if all their reſpective Members had conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and had there avowed their be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng of the ſame judgement, which they have ſince diſcovered otherwhere.</p>
            <p>That the publique debt contracted by occaſion of the char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the late warre may be borne by the partakers therein on that ſide, which cannot make it appeare that they had juſt cauſe to take up armes becauſe they could not obtaine juſtice by the Law of the Land, in ſome thing that was either of abſolute neceſſity to be maintained for the publique weale, or at leaſt of ſuch importance as was worthy to be contended about by arms; (there being no other ſufficient cauſe for the beginning of a ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill Warre, even by them that have unqueſtionable authority to make one:) And if both parties ſhould chance to faile in the proofe thereof, (which is not impoſſible in the generall, howſoever it may fall out in this particular caſe,) that in this e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent either every private man may beare ſuch part of the dama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges as hath fallen to his ſhare, or elſe that ſuch courſe may be taken for the dividing of this heavie burden among all them that are of ability to beare any part thereof, as may make it moſt eaſie to all, and oppreſſive to none of them.</p>
            <p>That if your Majeſty ſhould think, or be perſwaded, that the Lords and Commons now aſſembled in Parliament at <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minster</hi> are incompetent judges of the three laſt mentioned points, in reſpect of their being reputed parties in the late War, to whom notwithſtanding for the honor of the Parliaments of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:115305:11"/>
               <hi>England,</hi> we hope neither your Majeſty, nor thoſe Members of either Houſe, which have taken part with your Majeſty will be unwilling to referre either the examination, or deciſion of thoſe points ſo neerly and highly concerning your Majeſty and them; if the foreſaid Lords and Commons at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> ſhall be willing to binde themſelves by ſuch an Oath as hath beene above deſigned: Yet if we ſhould be miſtaken herein, or at leaſt in the third point, (which we do our ſelves obſerve to be of a different nature from the two former, the main queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in them being of matter of fact onely, whereas the chiefe controverſie in the laſt point may happen to be about matter of right:) and if all the former articles being by God's grace aſſented unto on both ſides, the happy concluſion of theſe unhappy broyles ſhould ſtick only there; In that caſe we crave leave in all humility to propound whether this difference may not be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodated by ſome ſuch expedient as this: your Majeſtie to make choyce of a certaine number of thoſe Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons which have continued in the Parliament at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and they to choſe a like number of thoſe that have withdrawn themſelves from thence by occaſion of the late troubles, and ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther all, or the third of the three laſt points aforeſaid to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the determination of the major part of the ſaid elect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed perſons in all that a major part of them ſhall agree in. But in whatſoever they may happen to be equally divided, the arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of ſuch point, or points to be referred to ſome one, or to the major part of ſome unequall number of ſuch ſtrangers fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous for wiſdome and juſtice, as may be joyntly choſen by your Majeſty and the aforeſaid Lords and Commons at <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter</hi> for the finall Umpirage of ſuch matter, or matters, as cannot be reſolved without the admiſſion of forein arbitrement, which is not without precedent in this kingdome. The which expedient, with all the former and enſuing parts of this
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:115305:12"/>our humble Petition, with ourſelvs, we do, and ever ſhall accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to our duty with all lowlineſſe ſubmit to the cenſure and reſolution of your Majeſtie and of your parliament, when we have firſt here ſincerely profeſſed out abhorring the leaſt thought of preſcribing any thing to thoſe whom we ought to obey, or of raiſing any third partie in armes, though never ſo great a multitude of Officers, and ſouldiers, and of the poor ruined people of the Kingdome ſhould teſtifie their adhering to us in our humble deſires by ſubſcribing hereunto.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, that becauſe there is ſmall cauſe to hope that this Kingdome can be at peace againe either within it ſelfe, or with your Majeſties other kingdomes, untill it and they have made their peace with God; and becauſe there is too much cauſe to feare that his all-ſeeing and all-diſcerning Majeſty hath been highly provoked by more than one of thoſe meanes, which hath been uſed to pacifie him, and namely at firſt by the long continued neglect of publique humbling our ſouls before him, for the preventing, or ſpeedy determining of a like bloody Warre in this kingdome, of which we ſeemed ſo ſenſible in <hi>Ireland;</hi> and ſince by appointing diverſe daies to that end by the divided authority of your Majeſty and of your Parliament, by faſting on thoſe dayes to ſtrife and debate: but chiefely by preſuming to come into the dreadful preſence of God upon thoſe dayes with much leſſe outward expreſſion of humble re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence and fear, then hath been ſhewed by heathen in the like occaſion; and with hearts fraught with bitterneſſe and wrath, and hands full of violence and bloud: and by the many diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſonant Confeſſions, Petitions, and thankſgivings have been put up to his Divine Majeſtie upon thoſe and other days: That in amendment of all theſe and other our failings, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-doings, and for the cleanſing of all your Majeſties Realms, from the blood wherewith they are certainly defiled, (if
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:115305:12"/>adventure any party, or perſon may waſh his or their hands from the guilt thereof,) ſome one or more daies, ſoone after that of your Majeſties meeting with your parliament, may up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their petition be ſet apart by your Majeſty for a moſt ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne humiliation of all the people of all your Dominions. And (as a neceſſary preparative thereunto) that there may be a convenient number of godly wiſe perſons choſen by your Majeſtie, your two Houſes of the Parliament of this kingdom, and the Commiſſioners of the parliament of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and that they may be authorized and commanded to make a pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and diligent enquiry after all the moſt crying ſinnes of all the Nations under your Majeſties government, and thoſe in ſpeciall for which it may moſt probably be collected that God hath viſited them all in circuit theſe laſt yeeres; as alſo after the moſt proper meanes to appeaſe the fierce wrath gone forth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt your Majeſtie and them, and to prevent the like in time to come.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:115305:13"/>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:115305:13"/>
            <head>A part of the DECLARATION of his Excellency Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax,</hi> now Lord <hi>Fairfax,</hi> with the Officers and Souldiers of his Army, ſigned <hi>John Ruſhworth</hi> Secretary, and dated <hi>June</hi> 14. 1647. Printed in the year 1648.</head>
            <div type="to_the_reader">
               <head>To the Reader.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y purpoſe herein is as to furniſh you with the abovementio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Declaration at a cheaper rate then buying the whole volume ſo to convince the Army of the expedience, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther neceſſity which lieth on his Excellency and his Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers to vindicate themſelves from the common imputation mentioned in the <hi>Poſtſcript</hi> of the foregoing generall <hi>Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> to that end only, and not from any evill affection towards his Excellency or any of them, excepting <hi>Levellers</hi> of what rank ſoever, of whom the Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of that <hi>Letter</hi> doth here publiquely profeſſe his reſolute and utter diſlike, wiſhing them ſpeedily to repent, leaſt they be overtaken by that heavie ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence pronounced againſt them.</p>
               <q>
                  <bibl>PROV. 24.21, 22.</bibl>
                  <p>My ſon feare thou THE LORD, AND THE KING, and med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle not with them that are given to change;</p>
                  <p>For their calamity ſhall riſe ſuddenly, and who knoweth the ruine of THEM BOTH?</p>
               </q>
               <p>ANd <hi>Levellers</hi> all muſt be (though perchance all intend not ſo) that would have no King in <hi>England;</hi> In which reſpect I ſhall not eaſily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that any Nobleman, Knight, or Gentleman ſhould conſpire to pull down that Monarchy, upon which all the advantage he hath above other men doth entirely depend: although divers be given out in the whiſpers of that party to be favourers of that wild deſigne. Whom I hereby pray not to deſpiſe this advertiſement, but to take ſome occaſion ſpeedily to declare againſt it, before it to be too late. And as for the <hi>Levellers</hi> themſelves,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:115305:14"/>and their quondam Agitators in Army, City, or Countrey, ſince they allow of extemporary <hi>Lay-preaching,</hi> I hope they will take no offence at my having given them a text not to talk, but to think upon: which I wiſh them in their moſt ſerious thoughts to compare with that other, <hi>1 John 4.20.</hi> and then to aske themſelves, whether upon the ſame reaſon it be not a certain truth, that he who ſaith he feareth God, and yet feareth not the King, <hi>i.e.</hi> the Soveraign Power of what kind ſoever, which God hath ſet over him, whether in one, or few, or many, is you know what. For he that feareth (that is, honoureth) not the King, whom he hath ſeen, how ſhould he feare God whom he hath not ſeen? In deſpiſing thoſe whom God hath placed in authority, and in that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect called gods, the authority of God himſelfe is deſpiſed. They have not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected thee, but they have rejected Me, that I ſhould not reign over them, ſaid God to <hi>Samuel,</hi> when the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> had an itching to be altring the Government. But I will here break off this diſcourſe wherein my Love to the mens perſons and ſouls, though I hate their opinions and practiſes hath a little impertinently engaged me to fill up this ſpare Paper.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="declaration">
               <head>A Part of the Armies DECLARATION of the 14. of June 1647.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow having thus far cleared our way in this buſineſſe, we ſhall proceed co propound ſuch things as we do humbly deſire for the ſetling and ſecuring of our own and the kingdomes common right, freedome, peace, and ſafety as followeth,</p>
               <p n="1">1. That the Houſes may be ſpeedily purged of ſuch Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers as for their delinquency or for corruptions, or abuſe to the State or undue Elections ought not to ſit there, whereof the late Elections in <hi>Cornwal, Wales,</hi> and other parts of the kingdom afford too many examples, to the great prejudice of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples freedom in the ſaid Elections.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That thoſe perſons, who have, in the late unjuſt and high
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:115305:14"/>proceedings againſt the Army, appeared to have the will, the confidence, credit, and power, to abuſe the Parliament and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and endanger the kingdome in carrying on ſuch things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us (while an Army) may be ſome way ſpeedily diſabled from doing the like or worſe to us (when diſbanded &amp; diſperſt, and in the condition of private men) or to other the free-borne people of <hi>England</hi> in the ſame condition with us; and that for that pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>poſe the ſame perſons may not continue in the ſame power (eſpecially as our and the kingdoms Judges in the higheſt truſt (but may be made incapable thereof for future.</p>
               <p>And if it be queſtioned who theſe are, we thought not fit par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly to name them in this our Repreſentation to you, but ſhall very ſpeedily give in their names; and before long ſhall of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer what we have to ſay againſt them to your Commiſſioners, wherein we hope ſo to carry our ſelves, as that the world ſhall ſee we aim at nothing of private revenge and animoſities, but that juſtice may have a free courſe, and the kingdom be eaſed, and ſecured by diſinabling ſuch men (at leaſt) from places of ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicature, who deſiring to advantage and ſet up themſelves and their party in a generall confuſion, have endeavoured to put the kingdom into a new flame of war, then which nothing is more abhorrent to us.</p>
               <p>But becauſe neither the granting of this alone would be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to ſecure our own and the kingdoms rights, liberties, and ſafety, either for the preſent age or poſterity; nor would our Propoſals of this ſingly be free from the ſcandall and appearance of Faction or deſignes only to weaken one party (under the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of unjuſt or oppreſſive) that we may advance another (which may be imagined more our own) we therefore declare,</p>
               <p>That indeed we cannot but wiſh, that ſuch men, and ſuch only, might be preferred to the great power and truſt of the Common-wealth, as are approved, at leaſt of morall righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe;
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:115305:15"/>and of ſuch we cannot but in our wiſhes prefer thoſe, that appear acted thereunto by a principle of conſcience and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in them.</p>
               <p>And accordingly, we do and ever ſhall bleſſe God for thoſe many ſuch Worthies, who through his providence, have beene choſen into this Parliament, and to ſuch mens indeavours (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der God) we cannot but attribute that Vindication (in part) of the Peoples Rights and Liberties; and thoſe beginnings of a juſt Reformation, which the firſt proceedings of this Parliament appeared to have driven at, and tended to, though of late ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed, or other diverted to other ends and intereſts, by the ☞ prevailing of other perſons, of other principles and conditions.</p>
               <p>But yet we are ſo far from deſigning or complying to have an abſolute or Arbitrary power ſigned, or ſetled, for continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, in any perſons whatſoever, as that (if we might be ſure to obtaine it) we cannot wiſh to have it ſo in the perſons of any, whom we could moſt confide in, or who ſhould appear moſt of our opinions, or principles, or whom we might have moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall aſſurance of, or intereſt in; But we do and ſhall much ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wiſh, that Authority of this kingdom in Parliaments (right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſtituted) that is, freely, equally, and ſucceſſively choſen, according to its originall intention) may ever ſtand and have its courſe. And therefore we ſhall apply our deſires, chiefly to ſuch things, as (by having Parliaments ſetled in ſuch a right conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) may give moſt hopes of juſtice, and righteouſneſſe to flow down equally to all, in that its antient channel, without any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertures tending either to overthrow that foundation of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and Government in this kingdom; or to ingroſſe that pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er for perpetuity into the hands of any particular perſons, or party whatſoever.</p>
               <p>And for that purpoſe, though (as we have found it doubted by many men, minding ſincerely the publick good: but not
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:115305:15"/>weighing ſo fully all conſequences of things) it may, and is not unlike to prove that upon the ending of this Parliament, and the election of new, the conſtitution of ſucceeding Parliaments (as to the perſons elected) may prove for the worſe many waies, yet ſince neither in the preſent purging of this Parliament, nor in the election of new, we cannot promiſe to our ſelves, or the king alone, an aſſurance of juſtice or other poſitive good, from the hands of men, but thoſe who for preſent appear moſt righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous and moſt for common good (having an unlimited power fixed in them during life or pleaſure) in time may become cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt, or ſettle into parties or factions: or, on the other ſide, in caſe of new elections, thoſe that ſhould ſo ſucceed, may prove as bad, or worſe then the former.</p>
               <p>We therefore humbly conceive, that (of two inconvenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, the leſſe being to be choſen) the main thing to be intended in this caſe (and beyond which humane providence cannot reach, to any aſſurance of poſſitive good) ſeems to be this, <hi>viz</hi> to provide, that however unjuſt, or corrupt, the perſons of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament men, in preſent, or future may prove, or what ever ill they may do to particular parties (or to the whole in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar things) during their reſpective termes, or periods, yet they ſhall not have the temptation, or advantage of an unlimited power fixt in them, during their own pleaſures, wherby to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuate injuſtice, or oppreſſion upon any (without end or reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy) or to advance, or uphold any one particular party, faction or intereſt whatſoever, to the oppreſſion or prejudice of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity, and the inſlaving of the kingdom unto al poſterity, but that the people may have an equall hope, or poſſibility, if they have made an ill choice at one time, to mend it in another, and the Members of the Houſe themſelves may be in a capacity to taſte of ſubjection, as well as rule, and may be inclined to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of other mens caſes, as what may come to be their own. This
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:115305:16"/>we ſpeak of in relation to the Houſe of Commons, as being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted on the peoples behalfe, for their intereſt in that great and ſupreme power of the Common-wealth (<hi>viz.</hi> the Legiſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive power with the power of finall judgement) which being in its own nature ſo arbitrary, and in a manner unlimited (unleſſe in point of time) is moſt unfit, and dangerous (as the peoples intereſt) to be fixt in the perſons of the ſame men during life, or their own pleaſures. Neither by the originall conſtitution of this ſtate, was it, or ought it to continue ſo, nor does it (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it is, and continues ſo) render that State any better then a Tyranny, or the people ſubjected to it any better then Vaſſals. But in all States, where there is any face of common freedome, and particularly in this State of <hi>England,</hi> (as is moſt evident both by many poſitive laws, and ancient conſtant cuſtome) the people have a right to new, and ſucceſſive elections unto that great and ſupreme truſt, at certain periods of time, which is ſo eſſentiall and fundamentall to their freedom, as it cannot, or ought not to be denied them, or withholden from them, &amp; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which the Houſe of Commons is of very little concernment to the intereſt of the <hi>Commons of England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yet in this we would not be miſunderſtood in the leaſt, to blame thoſe Worthies of both Houſes, whoſe zeale to vindicate the Liberties of this Nation, did procure that Act for <hi>Continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of this Parliament,</hi> whereby it was ſecured from being diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved at the Kings pleaſure (as former Parliaments had been) as reduced to ſuch a certainty as might inable them the better to aſſert, and vindicate the liberties of this Nation (immediately before ſo highly invaded, and then alſo ſo much indangered.) And this we take to be the principall ends, and grounds for which in that exigency of time, and affairs it was procured, &amp; to which we acknowledge it hath happily been made uſe of, but we cannot think it was by thoſe Worthies intended, or ought
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:115305:16"/>to be made uſe of, to the perpetuating of that ſupreme truſt, and power in the perſons of any, during their own pleaſures; or to the debarring of the people from their right of elections (to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally now) when thoſe dangers or exigencies were paſt, and the affairs, and ſafety of the Common-wealth would admit of ſuch a change.</p>
               <p>Having thus cleared our grounds and intentions (as we hope) from all ſcruples and miſ-underſtandings: in what follows we ſhall proceed further to propoſe what we humbly deſire for the ſetling and ſecuring of our own, and the kingdoms rights and liberties (through the bleſſing of God) to poſterity. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore upon all the grounds premiſed we further humbly deſire as followeth:</p>
               <p n="3">3. That ſome determinate period of time may be ſet for the continuance of this and future Parliaments, beyond which none ſhall continue, and upon which new Writs may of courſe iſſue out, and new elections ſucceſſively take place according to the intent of the Bill for Trienniall Parliaments.</p>
               <p>And herein we would not be miſ-underſtood to deſire a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent or ſudden diſſolution of this Parliament, but only (as is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt before) that ſome certain period may be ſet for the deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining of it, ſo as it may not remain (as now) continuable for ever, or during the pleaſure of the preſent Members; and we ſhould deſire that the period to be now ſet for ending this Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, may be ſuch as may give ſufficient time for proviſion of what is wanting, and neceſſary to be paſſed in point of juſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, and for further ſecuring the rights and liberties, and ſettling the peace of the kingdom. In order to which we fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther humbly offer.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That ſecure proviſion may be made for the continuance of future Parliaments, ſo that they may not be adjournable or diſſolvable at the Kings pleaſure or any other wayes, then by their own conſent during their reſpective periods, but at thoſe
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:115305:17"/>periods each Parliament to determine of courſe as before. This we deſire may be now provided for, (if it may be) ſo as to put it out of al diſpute for future, though we think of right it ought not to have been otherwiſe before.</p>
               <p>☞ And thus a firme foundation being laid in the authority and conſtitution of Parliaments for the hopes, at leaſt, of common and equal-right and freedom to our ſelves and all the free-born people of this land, we ſhall hereby for our parts freely and cheerfully commit our ſtock or ſhare of intereſt in this king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome into this common bottome of Parliaments. And though it m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y (for our particulars) go ill with us in one voyage; yet we ſhall thus hope (if right be with us) to fare better in another.</p>
               <p>Theſe things we deſire may be provided for by Bill or Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Parliament, to which the Royall aſſent may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired, and when his Majeſty in theſe things, and what elſe ſhall be propoſed by the Parliament neceſſary for ſecuring the rights and liberties of the people, and for ſettling the Militia and peace of the Kingdome ſhall have given his concurrence to put them paſt diſpute, we ſhall then deſire that the rights of his Majeſty and his poſterity maybe conſidered of and ſetled in all things, ſo far as may conſiſt with the right and freedom of the ſubject, and with the ſecurity of the ſame for future.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thus the Army the laſt yeer: The lip of ſincerity, as of Truth is ſtable for ever. Let them now declare their being ſtill of the ſame mind in the laſt, and capitall Article, the Peace is made. They under God ſhall have the honour to have made it, And the whole Kingdom will bleſſe them. For though by the Oath of Supremacy I have often taken, I think my ſelfe obliged to adde, That his Majeſty ſhall have great cauſe well to adviſe upon it before he part with his Privilege of diſſolving all future Parliaments without the conſent of the Houſes, upon the experience he hath had of doing it but in one; yet by his Majeſties having heretofore declared his inclination to treat upon the</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſals <hi>of the Army, I preſume this expedient to agree that Article, (the hardeſt of all other to be agreed,) would not ſtick with his Majeſty.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
